<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://melishua.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://melishua.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2023-08-13T18:51:58-07:00</updated><id>https://melishua.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Melissa Pan</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Why Master after 3 years of work?</title><link href="https://melishua.github.io/blog/2023/why_master/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why Master after 3 years of work?"/><published>2023-08-01T08:59:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-08-01T08:59:00-07:00</updated><id>https://melishua.github.io/blog/2023/why_master</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://melishua.github.io/blog/2023/why_master/"><![CDATA[<p>“CS don’t need degree from education systems”, “Anyone can become a SDE if you know how to code”. These are common statements that I have heard over the years even back in Universities. While some people say it as a self-mocking joke, it seeds the question on value of higher educations for CS in (some) people’s mind. Thus, many of my undergraduate friends are suprised when I expressed my interests in grad school after having a job as SDE.</p> <p>This question continue to follow me when I started my masters’ study at Carnegie Mellon University, and during my internship at Google. I think one of the root cause of having this question comes from ones’ perception on the objective of grad school.</p> <p>One point of view that I hear a lot is: “People go to school to find a job, if you already have a job, why school?”. There’s nothing wrong with this point if and only if all ones want is A job. It is easy for most of us (including myself at some point) to draw equal signs between education and career. You can literally look at the job decription of your dream job and evaluate what kind of degree is required.</p> <p>But set aside the minimal requirements (in typical case, because there are exceptions for sure), being a SDE don’t really have a hard requirement beyond a bachelor degree in most cases. So what does a master degree in computer engineering, computer science or related field provides?</p> <p>I have personally met a few people who pursue a master degree because they want to pivot from their undergraduate major. But that wasn’t the case for me either. I studies computer engineering at the University of Toronto, and developed solid foundatoins in computer systems, network, algorithms &amp; data etc…</p> <p>What is the advantage of a cs master degree? there are “About 419,000,000 results” on Google. Some of the common ones are:</p> <ol> <li>higher pay</li> <li>advance subject knowledge</li> <li>job growth</li> <li>competitive candidacy</li> <li>senior roles</li> </ol> <p>from source: https://www.coursera.org/articles/is-a-masters-in-computer-science-worth-it#</p> <p>But personally, my biggest motivation is that I have unfinshed dreams from undergraduate studies that I want to complete. I rather be doing it now and knowing if I like it or dislike it when I am yonge, than being at my 50s and regretting not taking the chance to complete my dream. And luckly, I have been liking a lot.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="life,"/><category term="school,"/><category term="education"/><category term="life"/><category term="school"/><category term="education"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[this is one of the most frequently asked questions I got since I decided to pursue a master degree]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Game of Life</title><link href="https://melishua.github.io/blog/2019/the-game-of-life/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Game of Life"/><published>2019-12-07T07:59:00-08:00</published><updated>2019-12-07T07:59:00-08:00</updated><id>https://melishua.github.io/blog/2019/the-game-of-life</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://melishua.github.io/blog/2019/the-game-of-life/"><![CDATA[<p>APS444 (happy engineering - positive psychology) is one of the best courses that I have ever taken in my life. The experience and lessons are truly life changing for me. I chose “inner peace” as the unit of building block for myself. And I’m glad that I discovered my inner peace.</p> <p>The following is a self-reflection journal I wrote after one of the class.</p> <p>Insights</p> <ul> <li>Play it is the feeling of enjoyment and the lost track of time when I am doing something interesting to me.</li> <li>Life will be fun if I consider everything as a game.</li> </ul> <p>Story “Oh my god!!! These were my favourite toys that I always wanted!!” I ran to the shelf that was full of barbie dolls and princess dresses as I entered Toys R’ US’. I leaned forward to look at a delicate holiday barbie set that could make a five-years-old me go crazy, and I continued my stroll. I didn’t feel anything wrong about this natural and “normal” behaviour. Why would I, a 22 years-old young adult, buy a barbie set? As I laughed to tell my team that I am not getting anything from the store, the my five-year-old’s dream was finally heard by the 22 year-old me - I want to have a barbie house when I grow up, I want to buy as many barbies as I want when I have financial freedom. When and how did my dream got lost in the interim of time? Why is my favourite toy no longer relevant to me?</p> <p>The doll was one of the most important toys in my childhood. My personality determined the play I had, or rather, my play shaped me and my character through time. When I was a kid, I was the shiest and most introverted girl in my class. I had no friends in kindergarten due to the language barrier. I used to only speak Cantonese, but I went to a Mandarin school. My happiest moment was to go home after school and start playing by myself. Roleplay with my dolls, read the children’s book or draw whimsically were my primary play activities at home. As much as my story may sound upsetting even for myself describing it now, I don’t think there is anything wrong with the way I was. My play formed a steady state of mind for me. Immersed in my own little world, I learned how to enjoy myself through coming up plot-lines with my dolls, I learned the principle virtues through reading the children’s literature, and I gained creativity through sketching everywhere.</p> <p>Yes, I may not remember my barbie dream now, but barbie is with me all the time with the self-enjoying and self-healing ability that she brought me. My childhood dream was not lost in the interim of time, my favourite toy is not unimportant to me, they just transformed into little units in myself that I did not notice initially. A sunny Saturday afternoon, a pile of books on the sun-warmed floor, few barbie dolls placed align listening to the five-years-old me with my grandma’s glasses teaching them animals, this scene may be left behind 15 years ago, but I took away the best gift from my childhood playtime – how to enjoy myself.</p> <p>Now, I learn the new definition of play. It is not associated with a toy or any objects, it is the feeling of enjoyment and the lost track of time when I am doing something interesting to me. Play is not barbie, play is not children’s book, play is not crayon set, play is the moment that I enjoyed my time with them. If I were to be asked what I, as a 22-years-old young adult, play now? I would probably answer scrolling through Instagram on my phone or watching YouTube on my laptop. But if I am asked for this question now again, with the new definition, there is so much more that I can add on my play list. I am roleplaying a real-life mentor by inspiring my cousin who is interested in STEM for girls, I am reading research publications that expand my knowledge, I am drawing system-diagrams for my capstone project. They share the same principle as my childhood playtime, but I never considered them as play before. Imagine how happy I could be every day if finding bugs in my codes is a treasure hunt game and going to lecture is watching the game tutorial.</p> <p>As a fourth-year student, I am approaching to the end of a game called – undergraduate life. I have had tears due to the time that I did not play out the game well, but I carried through firmly with the foundations I built. I have had laughers from completing the challenges successfully, which I can add these experience perks to my future game strategies. I am about to start the next level of the game soon – graduate study or industrial life. It can be scary for not knowing what to expect, but I am sure that I will be able to complete each stage of challenges and find enjoyment in life, with my definition of play, with the barbies in myself, and with my inner peace of mind.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="life"/><category term="life"/><category term="self-reflection"/><category term="inner-peace"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Self-reflection on what does toy means for me in life?]]></summary></entry></feed>